我们要把你送回未来了
We're sending you back to the future!
为何时间旅行如此有趣
Why is time travel fun?
开始了
Here we go.
因为有谁会不对过去好奇呢
Because who doesn't wonder about the past?
有谁会不对未来好奇呢
Who doesn't wonder about the future?
某人从未来回来  改变过去
Somebody comes back from the future to change what happened.
我们是在一部已经拍好的电影里吗
Are we basically in a movie that's already been shot?
我会回来的
I'll be back.
时间旅行故事接受各种可能性
Time travel stories embrace the potential
我们可能开启新的时间线  新的世界
that we might open up new timelines, new worlds,
以及我们人类的新未来
and new possibilities for ourselves as people.
那种能看穿一切的想象
That kind of imagination which can see through everything.
我们讲述关于时间旅行的故事时
What are we always trying to do
常做的一件事是什么
when we tell stories about time travel?
我常做的一件事是试图去感动观众
What I'm always trying to do is to touch people
触及内心
in the heart.
今天  我已经和你当年离开时一样大了
Today, I'm the age you were when you left.
你现在该回来了吧
This would be a real good tie for you to come back.
如果我们可以随意穿越时间
If we can go any place we want in time,
时间不再是我们的束缚
time is no longer our jail.
我们是由我们所经历的每一秒塑造而成的
Every second of our past makes us who we are.
而一想到我们可以重新经历一遍
And the idea that we could relive that
或者从另一个角度看一遍
or view it from another perspective
这种想法很人性  触及灵魂
is so human, and so spiritual,
我觉得它能感动所有人
that I think it touches everyone.
詹姆斯·卡梅隆的科幻故事
第六集
时间旅行
你基本上算是涵盖了
You've basically covered just about
时间旅行
科幻的方方面面
every base in science fiction,
时间旅行
科幻的方方面面
every base in science fiction,
外星接触  怪物  太空旅行  所有一切
from alien contact, monsters, space travel, everything,
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
导演  制片人
外星接触  怪物  太空旅行  所有一切
from alien contact, monsters, space travel, everything,
你还监制了
and you executive produced
史蒂文·斯皮尔伯格
导演  制片人
你还监制了
and you executive produced
《回到未来》系列电影
the "Back To The Future" series of films.
你觉得时间旅行是可能的吗
Do you think time travel is possible?
我和埃洛·莫里斯合作的时候
I asked Stephen Hawking that one day,
问过斯蒂芬·霍金
when I worked with Errol Morris.
有几个人能有这种经历
How many people get to say that?
但当时我和埃洛合作
But when I was working with Errol
作为他的监制  拍摄根据斯蒂芬·霍金的书
as his executive producer on the documentary
《时间简史》改编的纪录片
on Stephen Hawking's book, "A Brief History of Time."
我问了斯蒂芬·霍金那个问题
I asked Stephen Hawking that question
因为当时《回到未来》刚刚上映
because "Back To The Future" just came out.
而斯蒂芬·霍金回答说穿越到未来很有可能
And Stephen Hawking said it's very possible to go into the future,
但回到过去是不可能的
but impossible to go back into the past.
我们现在每分钟都能穿越到下一分钟
Hey, we're time traveling now at one minute per minute.
所以他算是在暗示一个事实
So he kind of was eluding to the fact
那就是《回到未来》里的一切都不可能发生
that everything in "Back To The Future" could never happen.
都是不可能的
Couldn't really happen.
《回到未来》
都是不可能的
Couldn't really happen.
《回到未来》
时间机器的一个经典设定就是
The classical idea of a time machine in which
《回到未来》
时间机器的一个经典设定就是
The classical idea of a time machine in which
你可以在某个时间点进入机器
you can go into it at one point in time
乔纳森·诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
你可以在某个时间点进入机器
you can go into it at one point in time
然后在另外一个时间点从机器里出来
and come back out the other side at some other point in time,
乔纳森·诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
这几乎是不可能的
it's almost certainly impossible.
乔纳森·诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
这几乎是不可能的
it's almost certainly impossible.
但拍电影的美妙之处在于
But what's beautiful about filmmaking
你不必听物理学家怎么说
is you don't have to listen to the physicist.
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
你不必听物理学家怎么说
is you don't have to listen to the physicist.
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
无论时间旅行是否存在
Whether or not time travel exists,
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
无论时间旅行是否存在
Whether or not time travel exists,
艾萨克·阿西莫夫
《苍穹微石》
无论时间旅行是否存在
Whether or not time travel exists,
本质上  它都是在主张自由意志
it speaks to that question of free will, essentially.
艾萨克·阿西莫夫
《苍穹微石》
本质上  它都是在主张自由意志
it speaks to that question of free will, essentially.
《进入盛夏之门》
本质上  它都是在主张自由意志
it speaks to that question of free will, essentially.
那才是我们谈论时间旅行这个主题时
That's the question we're playing with
《进入盛夏之门》
那才是我们谈论时间旅行这个主题时
That's the question we're playing with
《漫威科幻故事》
那才是我们谈论时间旅行这个主题时
That's the question we're playing with
《漫威科幻故事》
真正在谈论的问题
when we're playing with time travel.
《漫威科幻故事》
《时间陷阱》
真正在谈论的问题
when we're playing with time travel.
《时间陷阱》
它开启了无数迷人的思想实验
It opens up all sorts of fascinating thought experiments
《时间陷阱》
它开启了无数迷人的思想实验
It opens up all sorts of fascinating thought experiments
研究如何才能实现
about how that might play out.
在1980年的夏天
In the summer of 1980,
我发现了我父亲的高中年鉴
I discovered my father's high school yearbook
鲍勃·盖尔
编剧
《回到未来》
我发现了我父亲的高中年鉴
I discovered my father's high school yearbook
然后那道众所周知的闪电击中了我
and that was where the proverbial bolt of lightning struck.
鲍勃·盖尔
编剧
《回到未来》
然后那道众所周知的闪电击中了我
and that was where the proverbial bolt of lightning struck.
如果你可以和你爸一起上高中会怎样
What if you could go to high school with your dad?
如果你妈妈上的也是同一所学校会怎样
And what if your mom went to the same high school?
我是不是认识你
Don't I know you from somewhere?
没错  我是你的命定之人...
Yes, I'm your destiny...
谁不想成为自己父母第一次约会时
Who wouldn't want to be a fly on the wall
墙上那只小苍蝇呢  是吧
on their parents' first date, right?
《回到未来》
编剧
鲍勃·盖尔
在《回到未来》中
So in "Back To The Future,"
《回到未来》
编剧
鲍勃·盖尔
一个叫马蒂·麦佛莱[苍蝇]的孩子
a kid named Marty McFly
《回到未来》
编剧
鲍勃·盖尔
一个叫马蒂·麦佛莱[苍蝇]的孩子
a kid named Marty McFly
无意之间回到了过去
accidentally goes back in time,
扰乱了
and interferes with the event
让他父母相遇且坠入爱河的事件
that made his parents meet and fall in love.
马蒂遇到了两个问题
So Marty has two problems.
一个是他必须要回到1985年
One -- he has to get back to 1985,
但在这么做之前他必须得确保
but before he can do that he has to make sure
父亲和母亲之间的恋情
that he puts the love affair between his father
重新回到正轨
and his mother back on track.
每个人都有时间旅行的幻想
Everybody has that fantasy -- time travel --
克里斯托弗·劳埃德
演员
《回到未来》
每个人都有时间旅行的幻想
Everybody has that fantasy -- time travel --
克里斯托弗·劳埃德
演员
《回到未来》
我认为《回到未来》让这个幻想变得丰富起来
and I feel "Back To The Future" Just makes it so rich
克里斯托弗·劳埃德
演员
《回到未来》
我认为《回到未来》让这个幻想变得丰富起来
and I feel "Back To The Future" Just makes it so rich
用可能性  用孩子
with possibility, with a kid,
疯子  还有一辆德罗宁汽车
this crazy guy, and a DeLorean!
我的天
You know, I mean, it's just, my God!
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
我的天
You know, I mean, it's just, my God!
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
以前有过时间旅行的故事
So there have been time travel stories in the past,
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
比如查尔斯·狄更斯的《圣诞颂歌》
such as Charles Dickens' "A Christmas Carol,"
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
比如查尔斯·狄更斯的《圣诞颂歌》
such as Charles Dickens' "A Christmas Carol,"
《圣诞颂歌》  查尔斯·狄更斯
比如查尔斯·狄更斯的《圣诞颂歌》
such as Charles Dickens' "A Christmas Carol,"
史古基通过梦境里的幻想去旅行
in which Scrooge travels by means of dream visions
《圣诞颂歌》  查尔斯·狄更斯
史古基通过梦境里的幻想去旅行
in which Scrooge travels by means of dream visions
《圣诞颂歌》
史古基通过梦境里的幻想去旅行
in which Scrooge travels by means of dream visions
在里面他可以看到过去现在和未来
that allow him to visit the past and the present and the future.
《圣诞颂歌》
《康州美国佬奇遇记》  马克·吐温
在马克·吐温的《康州美国佬奇遇记》里
In Mark Twain's "A Connecticut Yankee In King Arthur's Court,"
《康州美国佬奇遇记》  马克·吐温
主人公的脑袋被撞了
our protagonist is bonked on the head,
《康州美国佬奇遇记》  马克·吐温
然后回到了中世纪的英格兰
and that's what returns him to medieval England.
《康州美国佬奇遇记》  马克·吐温
然后回到了中世纪的英格兰
and that's what returns him to medieval England.
《康州美国佬奇遇记》
然后回到了中世纪的英格兰
and that's what returns him to medieval England.
《康州美国佬奇遇记》
我们从不买那种东西的帐
We never bought that stuff.
《康州美国佬奇遇记》
我们从不买那种东西的帐
We never bought that stuff.
我们想让它变得合乎科学
We wanted it to be scientific.
一定要通过某种时间机器
It's gotta be via a time machine of some sort.
这样就会有发明时间旅行的人
So, that would be some guy who invented time travel
就在他的车库里
in his garage,
当然这个人就是爱默·布朗博士
and that of course is Dr. Emmett L. Brown.
博士
Doc?
别说话
Don't say a word!
我喜欢这个博士  他热衷于实现
I just loved this Doc who is feverishly trying to invent
一切他能想象到的发明
everything he could imagine inventing,
时间旅行当然是他最终的目标
and time travel of course would be the ultimate.
当这个宝贝达到时速141公里时
When this baby hits 88 miles per hour,
你就能看到厉害的了
you're going to see some serious shit.
他达到目标时的那种兴奋感非同寻常
His excitement about achieving that is incredible.
我很喜欢
I loved it.
悖论  第一场  第六条
准备  开始
Mark. Action!
悖论  第一场  第六条
准备  开始
Mark. Action!
像《回到未来》这样的电影
Movies like "Back to the Future"
告诉我们
provide a kind of tutorial about how paradoxes
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
告诉我们
provide a kind of tutorial about how paradoxes
怎样玩弄悖论
are things you can play with.
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
怎样玩弄悖论
are things you can play with.
《回到未来Ⅱ》
怎样玩弄悖论
are things you can play with.
在这个时间点之前  在过去的某处
Prior to this point in time, somewhere in the past,
《回到未来Ⅱ》
时间线偏斜了一定的角度
the time line skewed into this tangent,
《回到未来Ⅱ》
时间线偏斜了一定的角度
the time line skewed into this tangent,
产生了另一个1985年
creating an alternate 1985.
博士必须这么说
It's necessary for Doc to say it,
不是为了让故事吸引观众
not just for the audience to be caught up with the story,
而是因为他要说
but because he's gotta say --
"我必须这么做因为这件事如果发生了
"I've got to do this because of this because if that happens,
就会发生像这样的事情"
then you've got this going!"
马蒂  无论发生什么
Marty, whatever happens,
你不能让其他的自己看到你
you must not let your other self see you.
那样结果会很糟糕
The consequences could be disastrous.
不好意思  先生
Excuse me, sir?
他非常恐惧  只要有一个判断失误
He's in total terror that one mistake of judgment
整个宇宙就瓦解了
and the whole cosmos could collapse.
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
整个宇宙就瓦解了
and the whole cosmos could collapse.
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
这是每一个作家在时间旅行的故事里
This is the thing that every writer always struggles with
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
这是每一个作家在时间旅行的故事里
This is the thing that every writer always struggles with
总是在纠结的事
in time travel stories.
如果你回到过去  在那里
If you go back in time and something that you do
做了某些事
when you're back there,
造成了你祖父的死亡
causes the death of your grandfather
当时他还没有让你祖母怀孕
before he has impregnated your grandmother,
你因此不再存在
and you therefore cease to exist.
但是如果你不存在
But if you cease to exist,
那你一开始
then you weren't around
就不会进入时间机器
to get in the time machine in the first place
然后回到过去做那样的事
and to go back in time and do that.
所以发生了什么
So what happens?
他们管它叫祖父悖论
They call it the grandfather paradox.
记住了  按照我的理论
Now remember, according to my theory
你干涉了你父母的第一次见面
you interfered with your parents first meeting.
如果他们不见面  他们就不会相爱
If they don't meet they won't fall in love,
他们不会结婚  也就不会有孩子
they won't get married, and they won't have kids.
《回到未来》很明确地摆出了它的规则
"Back To The Future" Laid out its rules so clearly,
它实际上教给了电影观众
it effectively taught the movie audience
你改变了过去的时候就会发生这种事
this is what happens when you change the past,
这就是另一条时间线可能的样子
this is what an alternate timeline might look like.
还有一些可怕的问题比如
There are also kind of creepy questions like
你妈妈在青少年的时候爱上了你怎么办
what happens when your mom falls in love with you as a teenager...
安娜李·纽威茨
高级科技文化编辑
科技之美
最令人印象深刻的是
The most memorable piece
安娜李·纽威茨
高级科技文化编辑
科技之美
马蒂将自己八十年代的照片
is Marty's photograph of himself from the '80s,
安娜李·纽威茨
高级科技文化编辑
科技之美
马蒂将自己八十年代的照片
is Marty's photograph of himself from the '80s,
带到五十年代
which he carries around with him back into the '50s
并时常看看确信自己还在照片中
and keeps looking at it to make sure he's still in the picture.
被抹去存在
Erased from existence.
那张照片本身显然就十分矛盾
So the photograph itself is obviously incredibly paradoxical.
因为如果他的父母从未见面的话
Because why would his brother and sister be there
照片上怎么会有弟弟妹妹
if his parents had never met?
当初又为什么会有这样一张照片
And like, why would there even have been a photograph
诸如此类
in the first place?
但没有人会停下来想这些
But nobody ever stops to think about that,
因为我们已经制定好了这条规则
because we've set up this rule that says that
当马蒂从照片中消失时
when Marty disappears from this photo,
他也会慢慢消失
he's going to fade out of existence.
用完美的戏剧手法表现了
It's a perfect dramatization of the idea
从时间线上消除自己的概念
of erasing yourself from the timeline.
时间旅行电影某种程度上
Time travel movies sort of invent
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
时间旅行电影某种程度上
Time travel movies sort of invent
是创作最好故事的方法
whatever device will create the best story.
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
是创作最好故事的方法
whatever device will create the best story.
《回到未来》设了个陷阱
"Back To The Future" really set up a mousetrap
来建立起完美的悬念
to create the perfect kind of suspense.
*I'll be the vision of your happiness*
*Earth angel, earth angel*
*Please be mine*
时间旅行打开了各种各样的可能性
Time travel opens up a lot of possibilities.
你可以有另一种过去
So you can have an alternate history,
可以有另一种现实
you can have an alternate present.
乔治·麦佛莱被谋杀
可以有另一种现实
you can have an alternate present.
乔治·麦佛莱被谋杀
使我们有机会改变现实中许多
It allows us to change a lot of different weird things
乔治·麦佛莱被谋杀
使我们有机会改变现实中许多
It allows us to change a lot of different weird things
不同寻常的事
about our reality.
而且这种可能是无限的
And the possibilities are kind of limitless.
为什么我们许许多多的幻想
Why is so much of our fantasy, you know our,
在科幻作品中的想象
our imagination in science fiction genre
都是关于时间旅行的呢
taken up with this idea of time travel?
因为我们无法穿梭时间
Because we can't do it.
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
因为我们无法穿梭时间
Because we can't do it.
我认为在荧屏上看到时间旅行
I think it is just wonderful to see it on the screen
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
并且幻想自己身在其中简直棒极了
and imagine ourselves being in that situation.
阿诺德·施瓦辛格
演员
并且幻想自己身在其中简直棒极了
and imagine ourselves being in that situation.
我会很希望能够穿梭时间
I would have loved to be able to time travel.
想象我回到过去并且说
I mean, imagine to go back and say,
"我不会拍《大力神在纽约》"
"I'm not going to do 'Hercules In New York.'"
我叫赫丘利
My name is Hercules.
《大力神在纽约》
我叫赫丘利
My name is Hercules.
《大力神在纽约》
赫丘利  河秋梨  关我鸟事  把钱给我
Hercules, Schmercules. Give me the dough!
《大力神在纽约》
赫丘利  河秋梨  关我鸟事  把钱给我
Hercules, Schmercules. Give me the dough!
不会吧
I mean, it's like, unbelievable.
这就是你想回到过去做的事吗
That's the thing you want to go back and do?
不见见耶稣  不把希特勒干掉
Not meet Jesus, not kill Hitler.
你回去只想搞定一部电影
You want to go back and fix that one movie.
它困扰着你
This haunts you.
回去干掉希特勒或者回到古罗马时代
To go to kill Hitler or to go and be back in the Roman days,
要是能穿梭时间就棒极了
it would be really interesting to be able to time travel.
但问题是
But the question is,
如果在时间上来回穿梭是可行的
if you can move back and forth in time,
我们还能有自由意愿吗
do we have free will?
因为《终结者》系列电影的核心就在于此
Because "The Terminator" movies are kind of about that.
就是自由意愿
They're about free will.
如果某人从未来回来
If somebody comes back from the future
来改变当时的情况
to change what happens down there,
那我们岂不都是时间线上的傀儡
then are we just all puppets of a time line?
我完全相信你会弄明白的
I have total faith in you that you will figure it out.
《终结者》
《终结者》中一个有意思的主题讲的是
There's an interesting theme in "The Terminator" about
《终结者》
《终结者》中一个有意思的主题讲的是
There's an interesting theme in "The Terminator" about
马特·辛格
总编  影评人
打破银幕[美国电影评论网站]
《终结者》中一个有意思的主题讲的是
There's an interesting theme in "The Terminator" about
我们能不能改变过去
Can we change the past?
马特·辛格
总编  影评人
打破银幕[美国电影评论网站]
我们能不能改变未来
Can we change the future?
马特·辛格
总编  影评人
打破银幕[美国电影评论网站]
我们能不能改变未来
Can we change the future?
而你所看到的是未来回过头来毁灭过去
And what you see is the future coming back to destroy the past.
终结者从未来回来
The Terminator coming back to try to kill
试图杀死莎拉·康纳  带回凯尔·瑞斯
Sarah Connor also brings back Kyle Reese...
也就是约翰·康纳的父亲
Who becomes the father to John Connor
同时又是人类领袖之父
and creates the leader of humanity.
时间机器是将终结者和
The time machine was a mechanism to put the Terminator
戴维·杰罗尔德
编剧
《星际旅行》  《巴比伦五号》
时间机器是将终结者和
The time machine was a mechanism to put the Terminator
战士迈克尔·比恩带回过去的途径
and also Michael Biehn, the soldier, into the past.
戴维·杰罗尔德
编剧
《星际旅行》  《巴比伦五号》
战士迈克尔·比恩带回过去的途径
and also Michael Biehn, the soldier, into the past.
迈克尔·比恩
演员
《终结者》
战士迈克尔·比恩带回过去的途径
and also Michael Biehn, the soldier, into the past.
迈克尔·比恩
演员
《终结者》
那一角色是约翰·康纳从未来
That character was sent by John Connor in the future
迈克尔·比恩
演员
《终结者》
那一角色是约翰·康纳从未来
That character was sent by John Connor in the future
派回过去
to go back in time
保护这个女孩不被终结者伤害的
to protect this girl from the Terminator.
他们抵达过去后展开了追逐
Once they're there, then you have this chase,
谁能营救莎拉·康纳  还是她会被杀
who's gonna rescue Sarah Connor or is she gonna get killed?
科幻作品提出了疑问  我们命运是已有定数
Science fiction is a great place to ask is our destiny fixed?
还是能够改变
Or can we change it?
我什么都没做啊
I didn't do anything.
你以后会做的
No, but you will.
问题在于  我们是否被困在了一系列事件中
The question is are we locked into one series of events?
乔纳森▪诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
问题在于  我们是否被困在了一系列事件中
The question is are we locked into one series of events?
比如  第一部电影结束的时候
Like, by the end of the first film,
你看到了他们一开始穿越到过去
you realize you're seeing the creation myth
想要阻止的创世神话
of the thing they've gone back to prevent in the first place.
《终结者2  审判日》
想要阻止的创世神话
of the thing they've gone back to prevent in the first place.
《终结者2  审判日》
第二部电影揭开了这个可能性
The 2nd film opens up the possibility
《终结者2  审判日》
第二部电影揭开了这个可能性
The 2nd film opens up the possibility
并且莎拉·康纳直接与之对话
and Sarah Connor speaks to it directly.
也许那不是困住我们的世界
Maybe that's not the universe we're stuck in.
没有命运
也许那不是困住我们的世界
Maybe that's not the universe we're stuck in.
也许未来尚未写就
Maybe the future isn't written.
莎拉把刀插在桌子上  说道
Sarah sticks a knife in the table and says,
"世上没有命运  只有我们创造命运"
"There's no fate but what we make for ourselves."
她被告知她可以改变未来
She's been told that she can change the future.
但那是否只是个幻想
But is that just an illusion?
我们是不是在一部已经拍好的电影里
Are we basically in a movie that's already been shot?
胶片早就在某个地方卷好了
It's already rolled up in the can someplace?
有可能
That could be!
你可以随意快进或倒退
You can play it forward and backward as much as you want,
但结局永不改变
but the ending never changes?
我认为我们可以控制自己的未来
I think that we have control over ourselves
有能力去改变它
and I think that we have the power to create changes.
你儿子托我给你带个信
Your son gave me a message to give to you.
"未来犹未可知
"The future is not set.
你必须活着  否则我不会存在"
You must survive or I will never exist."
未来犹未可知
The future is not set.
是这样的台词
You know, I mean that's -- that's kind of the line --
未来犹未可知
the future's not set.
可以被改变
And it can be altered.
要我跟你说说你父亲吗
Should I tell you about your father?
如果你不让凯尔来找我的话  就没有你了
If you don't send Kyle, you can never be.
电影想要传达的是  你可以改变过去
The point that the film makes is that you can change history.
你可以逃离终结者
You can escape the Terminator.
但是时间旅行的重点不是过去
But time travel is not about history
也不是时间旅行本身
and it's not about time travel,
而是为生命中的
it's about accepting responsibility
各种可能性承担责任
for all the possibilities in your own life.
在科幻作品中
The idea of taking the wrong turn
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
在科幻作品中
The idea of taking the wrong turn
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
做了错事之后来弥补
and making a correction later on,
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
直面过去  对抗未来
《环形使者》
做了错事之后来弥补
and making a correction later on,
并不是一个新的创意
it's not a new idea in science fiction.
直面过去  对抗未来
《环形使者》
甚至在电影中也已经出现过了
It's not even a new idea in the movies.
直面过去  对抗未来
《环形使者》
甚至在电影中也已经出现过了
It's not even a new idea in the movies.
《环形使者》
《环形使者》说的是你试着
"Looper" Is one where you're essentially trying
《环形使者》
不去改变周遭的世界
to not change the world,
《环形使者》
而是改变自己的世界  改变自己的生活
but change your world, change your life.
《环形使者》
而是改变自己的世界  改变自己的生活
but change your world, change your life.
《环形使者》中  时间旅行者是个职业杀手
In "Looper," The time traveler is a hit man.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
《环形使者》中  时间旅行者是个职业杀手
In "Looper," The time traveler is a hit man.
你不知道吗
Wouldn't you know?
他是由约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
He's a hit man played both
和布鲁斯·威利斯共同饰演的职业杀手
by Joseph Gordon-Levitt and Bruce Willis.
当你决定成为一名环形使者的时候
When you agree to be a Looper,
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
《环形使者》
当你决定成为一名环形使者的时候
When you agree to be a Looper,
就注定不是一份长期的工作
it's not a long-term job.
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
《环形使者》
没有什么未来可言
There's not much of a future in it.
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
《环形使者》
没有什么未来可言
There's not much of a future in it.
有一天  你知道未来的自己
One day, you know that your future self
会出现在你面前
is going to show up in front of you...
而你不得不杀死他
and you're going to have to shoot it.
他的最后一个目标
That's gonna be his final hit.
就是杀死自己
To kill himself.
而他  所有的环形使者
And he, and all of the other loopers,
安娜李·纽威茨
高级科技文化编辑
科技之美
而他  所有的环形使者
And he, and all of the other loopers,
都达成了这个交易
enter into this bargain.
安娜李·纽威茨
高级科技文化编辑
科技之美
都达成了这个交易
enter into this bargain.
你不得不去做
And you have to do it.
如果你不做的话会有很大的麻烦
If you don't do it it's a really big problem.
更老的自己  布鲁斯·威利斯演的角色
The older one, the Bruce Willis character,
知道整个来龙去脉
knows the whole story.
而年轻的自己才刚开始意识到
But the younger one is learning for the first time what's --
发生了什么
what's going on.
他自然有很多问题
And he naturally has a few questions.
你知道会发生什么
So do you know what's gonna happen?
我不想谈时间旅行
I don't wanna talk about time travel
因为一旦我们开始谈论它
because if we start talking about it
那我们一整天
then we're gonna be here all day
都得耗在这里画图表
talking about it, making diagrams with straws.
布鲁斯·威利斯
演员
《环形使者》
谈及时间旅行
Talking about time travel.
布鲁斯·威利斯
演员
《环形使者》
会让你疯狂
It makes you go crazy.
和年轻的自己
And the option of going through a conversation like that
进行那样一段对话更让人发疯
with you at a younger age would make you even crazier.
让开
Move, damnit.
故事利用时空旅行来
Time travel is a device that
探索人性  探索人类对待彼此的方式
story is using to tell a story about human nature
以及在此之下的原因
and how humans treat each other and why.
让开
Move.
接着我看见了
Then I saw it.
假如说《环形使者》讲述的是
If "Looper" Is a story about how violence
暴力滋生更多暴力  对我而言
perpetuates more violence, to me, the lesson is
它告诉我暴力只能制造更多更糟的问题
that you just create more problems and worse problems.
我看见了  而这条路是一个循环
I saw it... and the path was a circle.
这是改变自身命运的故事
It's kind of about changing your own destiny.
也是讲述自身的命运是如何
And it's kind of about how your destiny
由其它更强势的人所决定的故事
is always being shaped by people more powerful than yourself.
你怎么才能真正挣脱一个黑暗的循环呢
And how do you really get out of a dark cycle?
影片指出了另一条终止循环的方式
The movie is pointing out another way to end that cycle.
所以我改变了它
So I changed it.
这是个实存困境
It is an existential dilemma.
源于萨特的哲学概念
指人对自身的人生与选择的一种困境
很多时空穿越都在探讨这个哲学问题
A lot of time travel is very philosophical in that way.
乔最终通过自杀掌控了自己的人生
Joe finally takes control of his life by ending it.
我们为什么迷恋时空旅行
Why are we fascinated by time travel?
人们总是问我
Well, you know people very often ask me
克里斯托弗·诺兰
导演  制片人
人们总是问我
Well, you know people very often ask me
为什么我对时间感兴趣  我说
why am I interested in time, I say,
克里斯托弗·诺兰
导演  制片人
"因为我一直活在时间里"
"Well, because I've always lived in it."
克里斯托弗·诺兰
导演  制片人
"因为我一直活在时间里"
"Well, because I've always lived in it."
我这样  我们都这样
It's -- I'm -- we are.
我们仿佛被困在时间中
We feel very trapped in it.
我们似乎是想要抓住每分每秒
It's like, we try to hang on to the moment.
我们什么玩意都拍下来  对不对
We take photographs of everything, right?
我们绝望地想要抓住当下的现实
We desperately want to hang on to
但它总会流逝
this reality and it recedes.
时空旅行让我们有机会设问
What time travel allows us to do is to say,
"要是我们能抓住呢
"Okay, but what if we could?
要是我们能扭转那一刻呢
What if we could preserve that moment.
要是我们可以回到那一刻呢"
What if we could revisit that moment, genuinely?"
这就是所有科幻作品的核心  设问
Well, that's all science fiction is about -- What if?
要是我们可以进行太空航行呢
What if we could travel through space,
要是我们可以进行时空旅行呢
what if we could travel through time?
《星际穿越》
《星际穿越》之所以具有如此的冲击力
What makes "Interstellar" so compelling
就在于影片创作者用这些桥段
is that the filmmakers devised these turns of plot
创造了一个真正经典的饱含感情的
to create a real classic family story
约翰·利思戈
演员
《星际穿越》
创造了一个真正经典的饱含感情的
to create a real classic family story
约翰·利思戈
演员
《星际穿越》
家庭故事
with the deepest possible emotions.
约翰·利思戈
演员
《星际穿越》
本质上  《星际穿越》是在讲述
Fundamentally, "Interstellar" is about
约翰·利思戈
演员
《星际穿越》
本质上  《星际穿越》是在讲述
Fundamentally, "Interstellar" is about
人类为时空旅行付出的代价
the human cost of time travel.
这是个非常专注于个人的故事
It's a deeply and intensely personal drama,
故事讲述了一名父亲
and the story of what happens
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
故事讲述了一名父亲
and the story of what happens
与他的孩子分别后发生的故事
when a father is separated from his child.
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
是"留下"
It says stay!
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
是"留下"
It says stay!
不  我会回来的
No, I'm coming back.
什么时候
When?
他会离去  拯救人类
Will he go and save humanity
还是留下  和女儿呆在一起
or will he stay with his daughter instead?
等到我回来的时候
I mean, by the time I get back, we --
说不定我们会一样大
we might even be the same age.
墨菲
Ah, Murph.
你都不知道你什么时候能回来
You have no idea when you're coming back?
《星际穿越》讲述了不久以后
"Interstellar" projects us into a near future
整个世界刚经受了一场
in which the world has gone through
巨大的全球灾难
an enormous global catastrophe.
尼尔逊在烧庄稼
Nelson's torching his whole crop.
枯萎病
Blight?
他们说这是最后一季秋葵了
They're saying it's the last harvest for okra.
再也没有了
Ever.
我饰演库珀的岳父
I play Cooper's father-in-law.
马修·麦康纳饰演前宇航员库珀
Matthew McConaughey plays Cooper, a former astronaut,
他几经周折
who by several turns of plot,
最终飞向外太空
goes shooting into outer space.
我们得移民到另一颗星球上  否则无法生存
We've got to move to another planet or we'll not survive.
《星际穿越》是一部不同寻常的时空旅行电影
"Interstellar" is an unusual time travel film
影片并没有制造时空旅行机器
because instead of building a literal time machine
埃米·尼克尔森
影评人  主持人
佳能秀
影片并没有制造时空旅行机器
because instead of building a literal time machine
然后讲述发明创造
and having it be about an invention,
埃米·尼克尔森
影评人  主持人
佳能秀
然后讲述发明创造
and having it be about an invention,
而是聚焦于空间对时间的影响
it's about the way time works in space,
时间因虫洞和引力
the way that it speeds up or slows down
加速或减速流逝
depending on wormholes and gravitational pull.
审视时空穿越
I think there are all sorts of different ways
有多种不同方式
of looking at time travel,
我拍摄《星际穿越》时
and when I came to do "Interstellar,"
那并不是一部时间旅行电影
which is not a time travel movie
但它具备这个要素...
but has that element in it...
-在影片末尾时间被折叠了  -确实如此
- It does fold time at the end. - ‭It does.
但你的设定依然十分严谨
You still approached it very rigorously
你拜访了许多业界顶尖专家
by going to some of the top experts.
这是全过程中最让我着迷的部分
It was a really fascinating part of the process
因为基普·索恩是最早...
because Kip Thorne who was one of the original...
基普·索恩
理论物理学家  诺贝尔奖获得者
因为基普·索恩是最早...
because Kip Thorne who was one of the original...
-我记得他来自加州理工  -没错
- Caltech I think. - Caltech.
基普·索恩
理论物理学家  诺贝尔奖获得者
基普是物理学界的大神
And Kip is one of the great minds in physics.
基普·索恩
理论物理学家  诺贝尔奖获得者
基普是物理学界的大神
And Kip is one of the great minds in physics.
他教会了我  当你把理论物理学概念
What he taught me is that once you can grasp
当作天体物理学概念来掌握时
those physical concepts as concepts of astrophysics,
它们会为你提供
they offer you this great launching pad
许多关于相对论
for story possibilities
以及其他科学理论的故事灵感
to do with relativity and all these things.
-比如时间膨胀  -没错
- Time dilation. - Exactly.
时间旅行有两种形式
There are two forms of time travel.
一种是不可能实现的
There's the time travel that is probably impossible
也就是回到过去
and that's going backwards.
而另一种时间旅行  不仅有可能实现
Then you have time travel, which is not only possible,
乔纳森·诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
而另一种时间旅行  不仅有可能实现
Then you have time travel, which is not only possible,
并且已经在现实世界实现
but already a feature of our world,
乔纳森·诺兰
编剧
《星际穿越》
并且已经在现实世界实现
but already a feature of our world,
也就是利用时间膨胀前往未来
which is time dilation forwards.
科学上有个被称为"双生子悖论"的理论
In science, there's this thing called the "Twin paradox,"
主要是说如果我的双胞胎兄弟登上一艘飞船
which basically says that if my twin gets in a spaceship
并且以接近光速的速度航行
and goes traveling at, near to the speed of light,
然后再回到地球
and then returns to Earth,
当我的那个兄弟回到地球时  他会比我年轻
when my twin gets back to Earth, my twin will be younger than I am.
西尔韦斯特·詹姆斯·盖茨
福特基金会物理学教授
布朗大学
当我的那个兄弟回到地球时  他会比我年轻
when my twin gets back to Earth, my twin will be younger than I am.
西尔韦斯特·詹姆斯·盖茨
福特基金会物理学教授
布朗大学
那也是时间旅行的一种形式
That's a form of time travel.
而这种形式在电影《星际穿越》中
And that is actually brilliantly illustrated
得到了很好的展现
in the movie "Interstellar."
快  快  行动
Go, go, go, go, go.
这里的一小时等于七年  珍惜时间
Seven years per hour here. Let's make it count.
《星际穿越》以最为先进的方式探索了
"Interstellar" Explored, in the most advanced way,
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
《星际穿越》以最为先进的方式探索了
"Interstellar" Explored, in the most advanced way,
时间旅行的实现方式
how time travel really might work.
约瑟夫·戈登-莱维特
演员
时间旅行的实现方式
how time travel really might work.
当他们前往那颗水星球时
When they go to the water planet,
时间的效应出现了差异
time works differently.
他们回到飞船上后
They come back to their ship,
那个留守飞船的人已经变老了
and the guy who stayed on the ship has grown old.
我等了许多年
I've waited years.
你等了多少年
How -- How many years?
到现在应该是...
By now it must be...
23年4个月零8天
23 years, 4 months, 8 days.
《星际穿越》中认为时间旅行总是会
"Interstellar" Suggests that time travel will always
带来相应的代价
have a certain kind of tradeoff.
在一方面  科学家拥有的
So on the one hand, the scientist's ability
穿越时空的能力对于拯救人类至关重要
to travel through space and time is essential to saving humanity,
但另一方面他必须踏上这段旅程
but the fact that he has to go on this journey in the first place,
永序号
太空探索
但另一方面他必须踏上这段旅程
but the fact that he has to go on this journey in the first place,
与他的女儿分别
and to be separated from his daughter
永序号
太空探索
与他的女儿分别
and to be separated from his daughter
在她大半个人生中缺席  表明了它的代价
for most of her natural life, suggests the very real cost.
你好  爸爸
Hey, Dad.
你好  墨菲
Hey, Murph.
你这狗娘养的
You son of a bitch.
影片中马修
There are moments when Matthew
可以通过录像
is allowed to see his daughter,
再次见到女儿
by, uh, video stream.
这样的时刻令人心碎
It's absolutely heartbreaking.
你曾说当你回来以后
You once told me that when you came back,
我们的年龄会一样大
we might be the same age.
而今天  我的年龄和你离开时一样大了
And today, I'm the age you were when you left.
现在你该回家了吧
This might be a real good time for you to come back.
人们常说  "我的孩子才出生  一眨眼
People talk about, "My kid was born, and I blinked,
马特·辛格
主编  影评人
打破银幕
人们常说  "我的孩子才出生  一眨眼
People talk about, "My kid was born, and I blinked,
马特·辛格
主编  影评人
打破银幕
我就要送他去上大学了"
and then I sent them off to college."
马特·辛格
主编  影评人
打破银幕
这部电影讲的就是这个
The movie is literally about that.
马特·辛格
主编  影评人
打破银幕
这部电影讲的就是这个
The movie is literally about that.
那些你毕生追求的事业
The sacrifices that go along with whatever it is
所带来的牺牲
that you've given your life to,
以你与家人相聚的时间为代价
at the expense of these moments with your family,
我觉得这是《星际穿越》的诗意所在
which I think is the very poetic part of "Interstellar."
如果说《星际穿越》探索了时间旅行的代价
So if "Interstellar" Explores the human cost of time travel,
那么《命运之门》也做了相同的事
"Primer" Does something very similar,
不过是从不同的角度进行的
but it does so in a different way.
我们看到两个平凡的工程师
We have two everyday engineers
无意间创造了时间旅行
who accidentally create time travel.
有想法吗
Anything?
-这正常吗  -我不知道
- Is this normal? - I don't know.
有些人认为这是最可信
Some people think it's the most credible,
最复杂的时间旅行题材电影
complicated, time travel movie.
杰夫·高布伦
演员
最复杂的时间旅行题材电影
complicated, time travel movie.
杰夫·高布伦
演员
它的拍摄成本非常低
It's done on a very low budget.
杰夫·高布伦
演员
你知道那部片的导演是谁吗
Do you know who directed that?
杰夫·高布伦
演员
你知道那部片的导演是谁吗
Do you know who directed that?
沙恩·卡鲁斯
Shane Carruth.
他自导自演  特别帅气
He's in it, he's lovely in it.
它在干什么
What's it doing?
我不确定是不是我的错觉
I don't know if I'm making it up...
这两个人  亚伯和亚伦
These two guys, Abe and Aaron,
一直在研究这个现象
keep investigating this phenomenon.
他们的实验中出现了一个奇怪的情况
There's this weird anomaly that shows up.
最终他们发现他们创造出
What they finally realize is that they have created a space
一个可以实现时间旅行的空间
that you can travel through time in.
沙恩·卡鲁斯
演员  导演
《命运之门》
一个可以实现时间旅行的空间
that you can travel through time in.
他们用这个原理造了一个更大的盒子
So they take this, and create a bigger box,
沙恩·卡鲁斯
演员  导演
《命运之门》
他们用这个原理造了一个更大的盒子
So they take this, and create a bigger box,
大到可以容纳人
big enough for a human to be in.
一开始他们使用时间旅行的目的非常世俗
When they do this, they use it for really mundane
非常符合一般人的想法
and very human purposes.
其中一人以此来炒股
One uses it to play the stock market.
时间旅行最终让朋友离间
And time travel ends up pulling the friends apart.
我只想知道你用了哪个盒子
I just want to know what box you used.
你只给自己造了一个盒子  对吧  只有一个
You built the one for you, right? Just the one?
对啊  不然你觉得我造了多少个
Yeah. ‭How many do you think I made?
他们互相怀疑对方
They are suspicious of each other
安娜李·纽威茨
科技文化资深编辑
科技之美
他们互相怀疑对方
They are suspicious of each other
又在互相欺骗对方
and they're also deceiving each other
安娜李·纽威茨
科技文化资深编辑
科技之美
又在互相欺骗对方
and they're also deceiving each other
因为穿越回过去影响了
because something about going back in time
他们的大脑
affects their brain,
他们真的日渐癫狂
and they do start losing their minds.
如同其他电影  《命运之门》明确暗示
Like many other movies, "Primer" does indeed suggest
时间旅行要付出代价
that there is a cost to time travel,
在这部电影里  代价体现在心理以及身体上
and in this case the cost is both emotional and physical.
你手怎么了  在流血吗
What's on your hand? Are you bleeding?
我们看到电影里的角色
So when we start seeing our characters show up,
他们耳朵流血
and they've got, you know, bloody ears,
不知道怎么写字
and they lose the ability to write,
右手写的字像左手写的
their right-handed writing looks like their left-handed writing,
他们大脑出现的问题
there's something going on mentally
正是他们付出的代价
that they are paying the price with.
时间旅行的故事就像浮士德
The time-travel story, it's a kind of Faustian tale.
和恶魔讨价还价
The bargain with the devil.
任何事都是一种交换
Everything is a barter.
如果你把灵魂出卖给恶魔
If you sell your soul to the devil,
你便可以得到想要的一切
you can have everything you ever dreamed of.
但最终你会付出代价
But eventually you pay the piper.
谁不想知道过去
Who doesn't wonder about the past?
谁又不想知道未来
Who doesn't wonder about the future?
这个游戏到底玩了多少遍了
How many times has that game been played, you know,
基努·里维斯
演员
这个游戏到底玩了多少遍了
How many times has that game been played, you know,
如果你能穿越回过去  你想去哪里
if you could go back in time, where would you go?
基努·里维斯
演员
如果你能穿越回过去  你想去哪里
if you could go back in time, where would you go?
你还记得第一次听说时间旅行是什么情形吗
Can you remember the first time you ever heard of time travel?
"古希腊人一定提到过时间旅行
"I think ancient Greeks must have had time travel.
莎士比亚的作品也一定提到了时间旅行"
Isn't there some time travel thing in Shakespeare?"
对吧  但并不是这样的
Right? But there isn't.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
时间旅行很年轻  是个新的概念
Time travel is new. Time travel is a new idea.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
时间旅行很年轻  是个新的概念
Time travel is new. Time travel is a new idea.
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
H.G.威尔斯之前  时间旅行是不存在的
Before H.G. Wells, it didn't exist.
H.G.威尔斯
《时间机器》
H.G.威尔斯之前  时间旅行是不存在的
Before H.G. Wells, it didn't exist.
《时间机器》
H.G.威尔斯之前  时间旅行是不存在的
Before H.G. Wells, it didn't exist.
《时间机器》
造就威尔斯时间旅行故事的是一台机器
What Wells gave the time travel story was the machine.
《时间机器》
造就威尔斯时间旅行故事的是一台机器
What Wells gave the time travel story was the machine.
人可以造出这种机器在时间中穿梭
The idea that somebody could build a machine that would do for time
如同火箭在太空中一般
what rocket ships would do for space.
加里·K·沃尔夫
作者
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
如同火箭在太空中一般
what rocket ships would do for space.
加里·K·沃尔夫
作者
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
这个想法令人无法抗拒
And the idea was just irresistible.
加里·K·沃尔夫
作者
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
这个想法令人无法抗拒
And the idea was just irresistible.
在英文中  "时间"和"旅行"这两个单词
It's literally true that the words "Time" and "Travel"
从未被放在一起使用  直到H.G.威尔斯
in English were never used together before H.G. Wells
创造了这样一个角色  他称之为
invented this character that he called...
时间旅行者
The Time Traveller.
夜幕像熄灯似的突然降临
《时间机器》
青闰译  译林出版社  2012年12月
夜幕像熄灯似的突然降临
又一转眼就到了明天
实验室模糊不清  烟雾弥漫  随后越来越暗
明天的夜晚来临  接着又是白天黑夜
又是白天  越来越快
我的祖父在1895年写下这段文字
My grandfather, H.G. Wells, wrote that in 1895.
西蒙·威尔斯
导演
《时间机器》2002
我的祖父在1895年写下这段文字
My grandfather, H.G. Wells, wrote that in 1895.
这是《时间机器》的初版
This is a first edition of "The Time Machine."
刚开始  什么好卖他就写什么
Firstly, he was writing anything he could sell.
那些为我们所熟知的小说
The novels that we now know,
H.G.威尔斯
《莫洛博士岛》
那些为我们所熟知的小说
The novels that we now know,
那些伟大的科幻文学
which are these great science-fiction novels,
H.G.威尔斯
《莫洛博士岛》
那些伟大的科幻文学
which are these great science-fiction novels,
是在他从事记者工作多年后才写的
came after he'd spent years writing as a journalist,
H.G.威尔斯
《隐形人》
是在他从事记者工作多年后才写的
came after he'd spent years writing as a journalist,
但那个时候出现了大量革命性的
but there was an enormous amount of kind of revolutionary science
H.G.威尔斯
《隐形人》
但那个时候出现了大量革命性的
but there was an enormous amount of kind of revolutionary science
科学成果
going on at the time.
达尔文是在用几十亿万年的尺度
Darwin was talking about the history of human life
来讨论人类生命的历史
in terms of millions and billions of years.
考古学家当时也在做着同样的事情
Archaeologists were doing the same thing.
人类发展出了比以往更加宏大的时间观
Humanity was developing a longer view of time than ever before.
当我谈论时间的时候  先生们
When I speak of time, gentlemen,
我指的是第四维度
I'm referring to the fourth dimension.
H.G.威尔斯的《时间机器》中
H.G. Wells, "The Time Machine,"
他笔下的人物穿越到了未来
his character goes forward in time,
这没什么问题
no problem there.
安迪·威尔
科幻故事作家
倒回到过去  则是完全不同的事情了
Going back in time -- entirely different thing.
安迪·威尔
科幻故事作家
如果你回到过去  那么你将碰见
If you go back in time, then you start running
安迪·威尔
科幻故事作家
如果你回到过去  那么你将碰见
If you go back in time, then you start running
各种各样由因果关系导致的问题
into all sorts of issues with causality.
这一观点用一个词组来表达就是
And that's the view that's expressed in the phrase,
蝴蝶效应
the butterfly effect.
一个复杂系统中的微小改变或微小扰乱
A tiny change, a tiny perturbation in a complex system
会在很短的时间内产生巨大的
can have enormous and unpredictable consequences
不可预测的后果
in a fairly short time.
这要从雷·布莱伯利的《雷霆万钧》说起
And it starts with "A Sound of Thunder" by Ray Bradbury.
《雷霆万钧》
这个故事的基本情节是  你可以穿越到过去
The basic idea of the story is that you can travel back in time,
《雷霆万钧》
这个故事的基本情节是  你可以穿越到过去
The basic idea of the story is that you can travel back in time,
但你要留在这个悬浮的平台上
but you're going to be on this suspended platform.
你还可以射杀恐龙
And you can shoot a dinosaur,
但得保证它是即将死掉的
but it has to be one that was going to die anyway,
这样你就不会改变未来的任何事情
so that you don't change anything in the future.
可是有一位傲慢的猎人
And this fairly arrogant game hunter
走出了平台并杀死了一只蝴蝶
steps off and kills a butterfly...
回到原来的时空后  他的未来变成了
And comes back and his future has turned into
原来世界的反乌托邦的样子
this kind of dystopian version of his own world
他几乎认不出来了
that he barely recognizes.
布莱伯利创造了这些具有深意的暗喻
Bradbury creates these deep metaphors
这些暗喻很大程度上塑造了
that give shape to a lot of the way
强纳森·列瑟
《菲利普·K·狄克精选集》
这些暗喻很大程度上塑造了
that give shape to a lot of the way
强纳森·列瑟
《菲利普·K·狄克精选集》
人们后来所理解的诸如
I think people have subsequently understood
强纳森·列瑟
《菲利普·K·狄克精选集》
时间旅行的概念
ideas like time travel.
强纳森·列瑟
《菲利普·K·狄克精选集》
如果你在过去改变了一只蝴蝶
Oh, if you change a butterfly in the past,
强纳森·列瑟
《菲利普·K·狄克精选集》
如果你在过去改变了一只蝴蝶
Oh, if you change a butterfly in the past,
整个未来都将随之变化
the entire future might be different.
时间旅行故事的作家们在考虑
When writers of time travel stories
一切所发生事情的逻辑后果时
consider the logical implications of everything that happens,
他们就被困在这些悖论中了
they get tied up in these paradoxes.
罗伯特·海因莱因是第一位从时间旅行悖论中
Robert Heinlein is the first writer to get the pleasure
获得愉悦感和兴趣的作家
and peculiarity of time travel paradoxes
也发现了它们可以被反复不断地利用
and how they can be exploited again and again and again.
他认为时间旅行故事所面临的问题
He sees that the problem with time travel stories
并不成为问题  而是一个机会
isn't a problem, it's an opportunity.
他写了一些故事  包括《你们这些僵尸》
He wrote stories like "All You Zombies,"
但是它和僵尸没有任何关系
which has nothing to do with zombies, by the way,
它讲述了可能是有史以来最令人困惑
but it has to do with probably the most completely confusing
也最令人愉悦的时间悖论科幻故事
and delightful science fiction time paradox story there is,
这个故事被改编成了电影《前目的地》
which was made into the film "Predestination."
我能做到这个  我能改变我的过去
I can do this, I can change my past.
《前目的地》
我能做到这个  我能改变我的过去
I can do this, I can change my past.
《前目的地》
是的  你能
Yes, you can.
《前目的地》
你有没有想过改变你的过去呢
Have you ever thought about changing yours?
《前目的地》
你有没有想过改变你的过去呢
Have you ever thought about changing yours?
我从未偏离过自己的使命
I never deviate from the mission.
《前目的地》讲述的是
Predestination
一位雌雄间性的时间旅行者
is about an intersex time traveler
迈克尔·斯派瑞
导演
《前目的地》
彼得·斯派瑞
导演
《前目的地》
一位雌雄间性的时间旅行者
is about an intersex time traveler
她在生命的一开始是一位女性
who starts life as a woman --
彼得·斯派瑞
导演
《前目的地》
迈克尔·斯派瑞
导演
《前目的地》
她在生命的一开始是一位女性
who starts life as a woman --
后来被强迫转变性别  成了一位男性
is forced into gender reassignment, becomes a man.
然后这个男人穿越到过去
That man then travels back in time,
爱上了女性身份的自己
falls in love with his female self,
然后这位女性生了一个孩子
That female self then has a child
这个孩子成为了他们自己的造物
which ends up being the creation of themselves.
因此这是一个关于雌雄间性的
So it's an intersex time-traveling
时间旅行禁忌爱情故事
incest love story.
事实上《花花公子》杂志拒绝了这个故事
And in fact "Playboy" Magazine rejected the story
因为里面的性故事让《花花公子》的编辑
because all the sex made the editor queasy,
感到有些恶心
the editor of "Playboy."
我觉得这是因为跟自己发生性行为
Well, I think it had to do with the idea of having sex
而生出你自己的这个想法
with yourself to create yourself,
有一点疯狂
which is kind of crazy,
《花花公子》会对这样的情节有看法的
that "Playboy" would have an issue with something like that.
但那是1959年
But it was 1959.
这是一个古老的问题
Well, it's the age-old question --
是先有小鸡  还是先有蛋
which came first: the chicken or the egg?
而我们认为是先有"公鸡"
Yeah. We say the rooster.
有些事情是命中注定的  是吧
Some things are predestined, right?
我决定了你现在的样子
I made you who you are,
你决定了我现在的样子
you made me who I am,
这是个悖论  对吧
it's a paradox, right?
但它可以被修正
But it can be para-doctored!
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
二十世纪大部分科幻电影中
We've had time travel in science fiction movies
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
都有过时空穿越  为什么大家偏爱这个主题
for most of the 20th century, so I guess the question is why?
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
都有过时空穿越  为什么大家偏爱这个主题
for most of the 20th century, so I guess the question is why?
《时间机器》
都有过时空穿越  为什么大家偏爱这个主题
for most of the 20th century, so I guess the question is why?
因为这是在探索可能的未来
Well, because what you're doing is exploring possible futures.
《时间机器》
探索我们现在做出的决定
You're exploring the decisions that we make now.
《时间机器》
探索我们现在做出的决定
You're exploring the decisions that we make now.
它使我们能想象未来会怎样
It enables us to imagine what the future will be like
或者过去会怎样  如果我们与其互动的话
or what the past would be like if we interacted with it.
这是探索潜在未来非常重要的方式
It's incredibly important way of exploring potential futures.
未来就是现在
The future is now.
如此多的科幻电影都是关于这些聪慧的
So many science fiction movies are about these brilliant
科学家  天体物理学家  生物学家
scientists and astrophysicists, biologists.
而《比尔和泰德历险记》不是
And "Bill And Ted's Excellent Adventure" Is not.
马特·辛格
总编  电影评论家
打破银幕[美国电影评论网站]
而《比尔和泰德历险记》不是
And "Bill And Ted's Excellent Adventure" Is not.
《比尔和泰德历险记》
不会吧
No way!
《比尔和泰德历险记》
会的会的  泰德
Yes, way Ted!
《比尔和泰德历险记》
会的会的  泰德
Yes, way Ted!
某种程度上  《比尔和泰德》变得重要
In a way, "Bill & Ted" becomes important
埃米·尼克尔森
电影评论家  主持人
佳能秀[著名影评播客]
某种程度上  《比尔和泰德》变得重要
In a way, "Bill & Ted" becomes important
埃米·尼克尔森
电影评论家  主持人
佳能秀[著名影评播客]
仅仅是因为它如此与众不同
just because it's so different from everything else.
埃米·尼克尔森
电影评论家  主持人
佳能秀[著名影评播客]
仅仅是因为它如此与众不同
just because it's so different from everything else.
它引人深思  我们写这些电影的人
It makes you think what is wrong with us,
到底是怎么了
the people writing these films,
只能将未来想象成可怕的东西
if we can't imagine the future as anything but awful?
两个人就能成为英雄  伙计
Two dudes can be the heroes, man.
准备好了吗  泰德
Ready Ted?
准备好了吗  比尔
Ready Bill?
让我们回到历史中吧
Let's go back into history!
亚历克斯·温特和我成了比尔和泰德
Alex Winter and I became Bill and Ted.
基努·里维斯
演员
《比尔和泰德历险记》
亚历克斯·温特和我成了比尔和泰德
Alex Winter and I became Bill and Ted.
比尔·史丹利·普莱斯顿先生
Bill S. Preston, Esquire,
泰德·西奥多·罗根
Ted Theodore Logan.
太棒了
Excellent!
比尔和泰德都是学渣
Bill and Ted are idiots.
而老师说  如果我们历史考试不及格
And our teacher tells us that if we don't pass our history exam
亚历克斯·温特
演员
《比尔和泰德历险记》
而老师说  如果我们历史考试不及格
And our teacher tells us that if we don't pass our history exam
就要被开除
we're going to fail out of school.
那边车里的女士说
The lady in that car over there said
马可波罗是在1275年
that Marco Polo was in the year 1275.
所以说不只是项水上运动  我就知道
So it's not just a water sport. I knew it.
如果他们挂科  泰德的父亲就会送他去军校
If they fail Ted's dad is going to send him to military school,
而如果他们彼此分开
and if they're separated
埃德·所罗门
编剧
《比尔和泰德历险记》
而如果他们彼此分开
and if they're separated
他们就永远无法组成乐队  拯救世界
their band will never form and save the world.
埃德·所罗门
编剧
《比尔和泰德历险记》
他们就永远无法组成乐队  拯救世界
their band will never form and save the world.
出现了一个来自未来的人说
Someone from the future shows up and says,
我们来帮你们
"We're going to help you."
你知道蒙古人何时统治中国吗
Do you know when the Mongols ruled China?
或许我们可以问问他们
Perhaps we can ask them.
比尔和泰德当然可以接受这一切
Bill and Ted of course can accept everything.
伙计们  你们要穿越回过去了
Dudes, you guys are going to go back in time!
他们有点像活在现代的傻瓜
They're kind of like these modern fools,
有种永恒的乐观主义
of kind of an eternal optimism.
克里斯·马特森和我有一段非常有趣的经历
We had a funny moment, Chris Matheson and I,
写剧本时
when we wrote it we were not involved
我们没有参与电影的选角
in the casting of the film,
所以不知道谁来演比尔和泰德
and didn't know who would play Bill and Ted.
我们飞到电影取景地  亚利桑那州
We had flown to Arizona where we were shooting the movie
我们在麦当劳排队
and we were at a McDonald's in line,
站在前面的几个孩子
and we saw a couple of kids in front of us
看起来吊儿郎当的  我们就想
and goofing off and we were like,
"就是那些小伙子
"Those are the guys,
该来演比尔和泰德"
that's who should be playing Bill and Ted!"
那天晚些时候  我们见到了基努和亚历克斯
And later on that day we met Keanu and Alex
正是麦当劳排在我们前面的小伙子们
and those were the guys that were in front of us
我们就想  "这很完美"
at McDonald's and we were like, "That's perfect."
电话亭
我们就想  "这很完美"
at McDonald's and we were like, "That's perfect."
电话亭
如你所知  乔治·卡林留给我们
And you know of course we are bequeathed
电话亭
如你所知  乔治·卡林留给我们
And you know of course we are bequeathed
一个时空穿越电话亭
a time traveling phone booth by George Carlin
并通过时空设置了一个任务
and set upon a mission through spacetime.
我们从历史中收集各种各样的角色
We collect all the various characters from history
这将是你能拥有的最棒的报告
because that would be the most awesome report
因为能在其中看到历史人物本尊
you could have would be to actually have the real people there.
我们喜欢摆弄这些悖论
We love toying with all these paradoxes.
《比尔和泰德》这部电影我最喜欢的地方之一
And one of my favorite parts of the "Bill & Ted" movie
就是所有历史人物
is when all the historical figures are in jail
被关进监狱出不来
and they can't get out.
我们能用你爸的钥匙吗
Can we get your dad's keys?
-可以偷  -好想法  伙计
- Could steal 'em! - Good thinking dude!
报告完成后我们将穿越回两天前
After the report we'll time travel back to two days ago,
偷走你爸的钥匙  把他们留在这里
steal your dad's keys and leave them here.
看到了吧
See?!
所以报告完成后我们千万不能忘了
So after the report we can't forget to do this
否则这就不会发生
otherwise it won't happen.
泰德就像是在通过现在的自己
Ted is like connecting to his future self
与未来的自己联系
through his present self to know
来知道未来他会把钥匙藏在哪里
where his future self will want to hide the keys
因为未来的他已经知道过去的他做了什么
because the future self already knows what the past self did,
但是过去的他不知道未来的他会做什么
but the past self doesn't know what the future self did,
但是他知道自己的性格
but he knows the character.
来吧  泰德
Come on, Ted.
我们该去救几个历史人物了
We've got some historical figures to rescue.
而这完美地概括了
And it perfectly encapsulates the absurdity
时间旅行悖论的荒谬性
of the time travel paradox.
你只要记得过去已经做过一件事
You just have to remind yourself to have done them in the past
你就会在未来做这件事
and they will be done in the future.
我就想这真是太厉害了
And I just thought that was terrific.
就像是在说  好吧  别担心
It just says, yeah, don't worry about it.
很有意思的是  在科幻电影的历史长河中
It's pretty fascinating honestly how rare
《比尔和泰德历险记》
编剧  克里斯·马特森与埃德·所罗门
很有意思的是  在科幻电影的历史长河中
It's pretty fascinating honestly how rare
《比尔和泰德历险记》
"Bill & Ted's Excellent Adventure"
编剧  克里斯·马特森与埃德·所罗门
这样的电影是非常罕见的
is in the grand history of sci-fi films.
《比尔和泰德历险记》
编剧  克里斯·马特森与埃德·所罗门
这样的电影是非常罕见的
is in the grand history of sci-fi films.
能有这种"哦  太有趣了"的科幻电影
To have a sci-fi film that says, "Eh! This is just fun!"
带给人一种奇妙的解脱感
is an incredible strange relief.
不可能
No way!
它不是唯一一部
It's not the only science fiction film
拿时间旅行玩得很开心的电影
to have fun with time travel.
事实上  这部喜剧片第一次普及了
In fact, this comedy was the first to popularize
《土拨鼠之日》
事实上  这部喜剧片第一次普及了
In fact, this comedy was the first to popularize
一种特殊的时间旅行即时间循环
a particular form of time travel called the time loop.
《土拨鼠之日》
丽塔  我在一次又一次地重新度过同一天
Rita, I'm re-living ‭the same day over and over.
《土拨鼠之日》
丽塔  我在一次又一次地重新度过同一天
Rita, I'm re-living ‭the same day over and over.
《土拨鼠之日》
土拨鼠之日  今天
Groundhog Day. Today.
北美地区的一个传统节日  每年2月2日
与预报时令有关
《土拨鼠之日》把时间循环作为手段
"Groundhog Day" uses the device of a time loop
来探索你要如何才能改善自己
as a way to explore ways you need to work on yourself
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
来探索你要如何才能改善自己
as a way to explore ways you need to work on yourself
直到你变得成熟并且能够与他人
before you can grow up and have meaningful
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
保持有意义的关系
relationships with other people.
丽莎·亚斯泽克
科幻研究教授
佐治亚理工学院
保持有意义的关系
relationships with other people.
《土拨鼠之日》
编剧  丹尼·鲁宾
我当时搞头脑风暴想点子的时候
When I was first brainstorming ideas,
《土拨鼠之日》
编剧  丹尼·鲁宾
我当时搞头脑风暴想点子的时候
When I was first brainstorming ideas,
丹尼·鲁宾
编剧
《土拨鼠之日》
我当时搞头脑风暴想点子的时候
When I was first brainstorming ideas,
我在那种小小的索引卡上写了
I actually wrote on the little index card,
丹尼·鲁宾
编剧
《土拨鼠之日》
我在那种小小的索引卡上写了
I actually wrote on the little index card,
时间机器
"Time machine."
但是我不知道应该涉及什么
But I didn't really know what was going to be involved
或它是怎么运作的
or how it was going to work.
菲尔  菲尔  菲尔·康纳斯
Phil? Phil?! Phil Connors?
菲尔·康纳斯  我就知道是你
Phil Connors, I thought that was you.
我就想  好吧  不管怎么样  规则就是
I just thought, "Okay, whatever it is the rule is,
他可以记得  但是其他人不能记得
he can remember, but nobody else can remember.
所以对他们来说就是同一天
So for them it's just the same day.
而对他来说则是许多漫长的  重复的日子
And for him it's part of a long, long, long repetition of days."
而观众会学会期待这一点
And the audience learns to expect that,
他们可以和主角一起整理这一天的情况
and can begin to sort of map the day along with the character
并且尝试在主角之前找出
and see if they can figure out
脱离时间循环的方法
how to get out of this time loop before he does.
真正的时间机器  是你的大脑
The real time travel machine, is your brain.
在那里  我们时刻在回看
In here, we're constantly recoiling
强纳森·列瑟
作家  编辑
《菲利普·K·狄克小说精选》
在那里  我们时刻在回看
In here, we're constantly recoiling
强纳森·列瑟
作家  编辑
《菲利普·K·狄克小说精选》
不同时期的自己  回忆
through different versions of ourselves, memories,
强纳森·列瑟
作家  编辑
《菲利普·K·狄克小说精选》
不同时期的自己  回忆
through different versions of ourselves, memories,
白日梦  还有不同的可能性
and daydreams, alternate paths,
在其中  我们可能到达别的现实
where we might end up somewhere different.
你有记忆幻觉吗   兰卡斯特夫人
Do you ever have déjà vu, Mrs. Lancaster?
应该没有  但是我可以去问一问厨房
I don't think so, but I could check with the kitchen?
而这就是时间旅行帮我们提纯出来的
And this is what the time travel story crystallizes for us.
这是一种意识的模型
It's a model of consciousness,
在时间中时刻充满着究极的自由
which is constantly reeling with ultimate freedom through time,
但是最后不得不发现自己还是被困在现实世界
and then finding itself stuck, once again, in the real world.
在 《土拨鼠之日》的第一部分
In the first stretch of "Groundhog Day,"
比尔·莫瑞知道自己身上将要发生的所有事
Bill Murray knows everything that's gonna happen to him,
他可以利用这些  为自己谋利
he can make that work to his advantage.
他采取的手段就像是青少年会做的
And he does it in the way an adolescent would,
纯粹为了取乐  或者说像是一个反社会人格
just having fun and also becoming kind of sociopathic.
他不在乎其他人
You don't really care about the other people.
他们就是他生活中的道具
They are objects in your life.
然后下一个阶段是抑郁
And then it moves on to a depression
他最终决定自杀
where he finally decides to kill himself.
然而他发现他无法做到
And he finds that he cannot even do that.
这是汤姆  他以前在煤矿工作
This is Tom, he worked in the coal mine
后来矿倒闭了
until they closed it down.
这里是他第一次
This is where he, for the first time
开始意识到其他人
starts to notice other people,
意识到他们也有自己的生活
and realizes that they have lives, too,
他是社区的一员
and that he's part of a community
通过重新认识自己
and by seeing himself differently,
他也开始重新认识世界
he actually opens up a whole new world to himself.
老人家  我们去个暖和点的地方吧
Hello, father, let's get yourself someplace warm.
困在时间循环里的好处在于
The wonderful thing about being stuck in a time loop,
我们能从不同的角度审视自己的生活
it makes us look at our lives in a fresh way
这也是电影其中一个好处
which is one of the great things that movies can do,
特别是科幻作品
and especially science fiction,
因为它即刻就能让你
because it can so immediately place you
置身于不同的时空
in a different time and place.
也许我们都需要一部时间旅行电影
Maybe we all do need a time travel movie
让我们能成为更好的自己
to make us a better version of ourselves,
希望我们不要像他被困这么长时间就好
but I hope that we're not stuck as long as he is.
只要有一点不同就很棒
Anything different is good.
我的名字是神秘博士
My name is Doctor Who.
《神秘博士》
我的名字是神秘博士
My name is Doctor Who.
《神秘博士》
不是吧  真的吗
It's not, is it?
《神秘博士》
我挺喜欢的
I like it.
《神秘博士》
你还不知道
You don't know it yet.
《神秘博士》
你还不知道
You don't know it yet.
但不需多久  你就会用生命信任我
But in a short time, you will trust me with your life.
警亭
但不需多久  你就会用生命信任我
But in a short time, you will trust me with your life.
警亭
《神秘博士》是非常英式  有点古怪
"Doctor Who" is a very British, slightly eccentric
警亭
《神秘博士》是非常英式  有点古怪
"Doctor Who" is a very British, slightly eccentric
却异常精彩的电视系列
extraordinary series
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
却异常精彩的电视系列
extraordinary series
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
这部作品已经有五十多年历史
that's been running for more than 50 years now.
亚当·卢瑟福
科学记者
BBC第四频道
这部作品已经有五十多年历史
that's been running for more than 50 years now.
主角是一位性格古怪又富有魅力的时间领主
And it involves a charming, peculiar Time Lord.
我们是时间旅行者  我们谨言慎行
We're time travelers. We tread softly.
他来自外星  保护着我们
He's an alien who has come down to protect us
不受宇宙其他星球的侵扰  他穿梭于时间
from the rest of the universe by traveling through time
穿梭于过去和未来的
and by interacting with real historical events
各种事件
in both the past and the future.
我们没带武器
We're unarmed.
你不会对手无寸铁的平民开火吧
You wouldn't open fire on an unarmed civilians would you?
这也不会是第一次了
It wouldn't be the first time.
活宝  就是现在
Chuckles, now!
我爱《神秘博士》
Oh, I love "Doctor Who."
安迪·威尔
科幻作家
我爱《神秘博士》
Oh, I love "Doctor Who."
安迪·威尔
科幻作家
在过去五十多年中  共有十二任博士
Over the past 50 years there have been a total of 12 Doctor Whos.
每位出演者都带来了新的特色
Each new performer brings his own thing to it.
我真的看过《神秘博士》的每一集
I've seen literally every episode of "Doctor Who"
从第一集《神秘孩子》
that's ever been made from "An Unearthly Child,"
制作于1963年
which was made in 1963,
到现在彼得·卡帕尔蒂饰演的博士
all the way up to the current Peter Capaldi Doctor Whos.
你是黑暗的一方  你是戴立克的敌人
You are the dark side, you are an enemy of the Daleks.
是的没错
Oh, yes, I am.
消灭
Exterminate!
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
我是看这部剧长大的
I grew up with the show.
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
我小时候住在苏格兰格拉斯哥的经济公寓里
I lived in a tenement in Glasgow in Scotland,
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
通过那些闪烁的蓝色画面
and through these flickering little blue images
彼得·卡帕尔蒂
演员
《神秘博士》
通过那些闪烁的蓝色画面
and through these flickering little blue images
我像是去到了不同的星球
I'd be taken to other planets with strange creatures
看到了充满想象力的新奇事物
with wonderful imaginative designs.
你觉得你是第一个想要杀死我的人吗
Do you think you're the first to try and kill me?
《神秘博士》总有点廉价电影的感觉
And also there has always been a kind of B-movie element to it,
我一直很喜欢
which I've always loved.
-这里有什么邪恶吗  -没什么东西邪恶
- Is everything out here evil? - Hardly anything is evil.
大多数只是饿了
But most things are hungry.
从食物链的另一端看  饥饿就是邪恶
Hunger looks very like evil from the wrong end of the cutlery
你认为你的培根三明治也爱你吗
or do you think that your bacon sandwich loves you back?
我认为《神秘博士》很有魅力的一点
I think one of the things that's appealing about "Doctor Who,"
在于他的英式幽默
is there's a tradition of English humor
加里·K·沃尔夫
作家
《伟大的科幻小说作品是怎样炼成的》
在于他的英式幽默
is there's a tradition of English humor
好像未来就是一个笑话
which suggests that the future is all a joke.
他是位时间领主
He's a Time Lord, yes.
他能在时间线中自如穿梭
And he can travel back and forth in time,
但他老做些荒唐可笑的事情
and he does it in absurd ways.
时间和空间相对维度
Time And Relative Dimension In Space.
简称"塔迪斯"
TARDIS for short.
博士的时光机  塔迪斯
The Doctor's time machine, the TARDIS,
是最棒的时间机器之一
is one of the best ever because it invokes
因为它包含着物理学
the playing with physics
是时空旅行中很必要的元素
that is going to be necessary to travel through time and space
他的塔迪斯里面的空间
because his machine is bigger on the inside
比外面看起来要大
than it is on the outside.
你的盒子可以移动
So your box can move.
我们能去我们想去的任何地方
We can go anywhere we like.
博士总有一个人类同伴
He always has a human companion.
他带着同伴
And he brings that companion
去各处探险
along with him on his adventures.
-我们在哪  -道路的尽头
- Where are we? - The end of the road.
最后的星球
The last planet.
他的心中仿佛人类总占据特别之地
He seems to have a special place in his heart for humans.
安娜李·纽威茨
科技文化资深编辑
科技之美
他的心中仿佛人类总占据特别之地
He seems to have a special place in his heart for humans.
选择普通人
Picking individual ordinary people
带他们见识所有的时间和空间
and showing them all of time and space
让他们更加全面地理解生命
and giving them a broader view on life.
他也是医生  医生会做什么
He's the Doctor. What do doctors do?
他们救死扶伤  拯救危难于水火
They heal sick situations, sick people.
戴维·杰罗尔德
编剧
《星际旅行》《巴比伦五号》
他们救死扶伤  拯救危难于水火
They heal sick situations, sick people.
可你为什么要毁掉这一切
But why do you have to destroy?
就不能动动脑吗
Can't you use your brains?
只有一个种族能活下来
Only one race can survive.
这是场邪恶且毫无意义的杀戮
This senseless evil killing.
博士的第一位扮演者  威廉·哈特内尔病了
The first actor, the wonderful William Hartnell, became ill
不能继续拍摄
and couldn't carry on with the show.
于是大家提出了一个非常棒的想法
So they came up with this rather brilliant idea,
让博士有重生的能力
which is that the Doctor has the ability to reconstitute himself.
这个设定让剧集得以延续
This has allowed this show to last
因为我们每隔三四年就会更换主演
because we change the lead actor every three or four years,
这是绝无仅有的
which no other show does.
它也有其他层面的哲学性
It has all these other levels of philosophical
引人思考
and reflective nature
让这部剧有着非常  非常丰富的内涵
that make it very, very rich.
人们总是问我  为什么这部剧
People always ask me what is it about the show
能吸引这么多人
that appeals so broadly?
我的答案呢
The answer I would like to give
虽然不情愿这么说
and which I'm discouraged from giving,
毕竟无助于剧集的推广
because it is not useful in the promotion of a brand,
其实整部剧讲的是死亡
is that it's about death.
《神秘博士》有非常强烈的主题  就是死亡
And it has a very, very powerful death motif in it,
主角全部死了
which is that the central character dies.
博士  放手吧
Doctor, let it go.
一切都来得及
Time enough.
我认为这是这部剧最为神秘的一点
And I think that is one of its most potent mysteries.
因为在剧中某处
Because somewhere in that,
人们能透过电视剧看到生活
people see that that's what happens in life.
你所爱的人离你而去
You have loved ones, and then they go,
但你的生活必须继续下去
but you must carry on.
在时间旅行的故事中  人们想了很多办法
There are a lot of ways in which time travel stories
偷偷地逃避死亡
sneakily are about eluding death.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
偷偷地逃避死亡
sneakily are about eluding death.
人的生命终将在时光中流逝殆尽
Time is what kills us, after all.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
时间这个混蛋
Time is a bastard.
詹姆斯·格雷克
作家
《时间旅行简史》
时间这个混蛋
Time is a bastard.
冥冥之中  我们的灵魂听到有关时间旅行的事
There's something that speaks to our souls about time travel
这有些宿命论的意味
where there's a fatalism involved
克里斯托弗·诺兰
导演/制片人
这有些宿命论的意味
where there's a fatalism involved
-但多少又让人觉得安心  -是这样
- that is reassuring somehow. - Right.
因为时间旅行能告诉你
‭Because it tells you that the mistakes
哪些错误会一直出现
were always gonna happen.
非常有趣的一件事是
I mean, one of the fascinating things --
有一天我向我的孩子解释说
I was explaining to my kids the other day --
可以用望远镜实现时间旅行
that if you look at the idea of a telescope.
望远镜能从时间上回顾过去
Telescope is a way of looking back in time,
-它是时间机器  -是空间角度之外的
- It's a time machine. - ...and not just space.
望远镜能从时间上回顾过去
Telescope is a way of looking back in time,
-它是时间机器  -是空间角度之外的
- It's a time machine. - ...and not just space.
望远镜就是时间机器
It's a time machine.
如果从更远处望向最小的那颗星
And you look at the smallest star, the further away,
你看到的是更加遥远的过去
the further back in time you're looking.
理论上讲  你可以造出
And theoretically you could make more
性能更强的望远镜
and more powerful telescopes,
这样就能看到更久远的过去
and you can look further and further back in time.
是个有些烧脑的想法
It's just a mind-boggling concept.
理论上讲  太阳很可能已经
Theoretically ‭the sun could have gone out
在七分半前熄灭了  而我们还不知道
seven and a half minutes ago and we just don't know yet
因为光传递到这儿  是需要时间的
'cause it takes light a while to get here.
没错  希望这种事不要发生
Exactly. Let's hope not.
就时间而言  你在回望过去的同时
But that idea of looking back in time
也在看向现实世界
as you look out into the world,
就在这间屋子里  你环顾四周
the fact that everything we see in this room
就是在回顾时间
when you look around, you're looking back in time.
我认为时间旅行故事
I think the potential is limitless
潜力无限
for time travel stories...
克里斯  谢谢你接受采访
Chris, thanks for doing this.
不  要谢谢你邀请了我
No, thank you for having me.
-光是谈论就让人觉得兴奋  -那很好
- It's exciting to talk about. - Okay. Good.
好了  可以帮我们喊停了
All right, give us a cut then.
我给你喊停吧  拍摄结束
I'll give you a cut. Done.
-结束了  -回家了
- Done. - Going home.